[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here we know about
markovnikov's rule which dictates that
in a reaction like electrophilic
addition when a carbocation intermediate
is formed it is specifically the more
substituted carbocation of the two that
are possible which will form but why is
this let's look at carbocation stability
to understand how this works first a few
details about carbocations these are
carbons with a formal positive charge
because they have lost an electron
domain because of this they are SP2
hybridized and trigonal planer so they
are totally flat about the carbocation
with 120° Bond angles this means that
there is one remaining unhybridized p
orbital and this will be vacant
extending on loes perpendicular to the
plane of the molecule now let's let's
revisit the mechanism for an addition
reaction to contextualize carbocation
stability recall that in the first step
of a hydrohalogenation a new CH Bond was
produced leaving us with a carbocation
but it was the case that the new
hydrogen ended up exclusively on the
less substituted carbon leaving us with
this specific carbocation which we can
call a tertiary carbocation since the
carbon that bears the formal positive
charge is bonded to three other carbons
in this case three methyl groups we did
not see the reverse situation where the
hydrogen ended up on the more
substituted carbon which would leave us
with this carbocation which we would
call a primary carbocation since the
carbon would be bonded to only one other
carbon the rest of the molecule only the
first pathway occurs and never the
second the reasoning behind this is that
carbocations become more stable as they
are more substituted meaning when they
have more adjacent alkal groups this has
to do with a phenomenon called hyper
conjugation where electrons in adjacent
CH bonds which are roughly parallel to
the lobes of the vacant unhybridized p
orbital lend some electron density to
the carbocation thereby stabilizing it
the more alkal groups there are adjacent
the greater the effect so the methyl
cation would be the least stable
carbocation possible followed by a
primary carbocation with one alkal group
then a secondary carbocation with two
alkal groups and the most stable would
be a tertiary carbocation with three
alkal groups this same phenomenon is
also behind the stabilization of alkenes
with greater substitution another reason
for this stabilization has to do with
inductive effects this refers to
electronic effects that are occurring
through Sigma bonds the electron density
surrounding alkal groups is more
polarizable through the sigma Bond
system than that around a hydrogen atom
so more alal results in a greater
inductive effect which is
stabilizing with that we understand how
hyper conjugation and inductive effects
both contribute to the carbocation
stability Trend which says that more
highly substituted carbocations meaning
those with more alkal groups will be
more stable Professor Dave for che see
you next
time
go